we stopped right
at we don't think we finished yes we didn't
finish So we have a clear
job work Dushka
will go to the
four
forces four forces you use When you
clear your bad
Seda five forces this is how to get a
good life How to create a good life
and
how
How good is death
So
while we
live we use the first
p there are two sets And when we get to the
hospital and we understand that we will not
get out of here
we begin to use the
next set of
five something
depressive the
essence of
namri is two things ri achieve two
things teach you how to live and teach you
how to die and our whole
culture in every country in this
world are afraid to talk about it they don't
want to talk
about they don't
think that
it's not very good to
talk but we all
Umm so let's better
prepare and it can be very
beautiful no matter how old
or
young when I was walking this
morning someone
said my relative very young about
died to me I felt
strange I'm already a clone of age and he is
young people die when something is wrong with them
sometimes young  sometimes it
doesn't matter what age at any age
m so we don't know when we
die Let's better prepare for this
and don't be so
serious okay Yes I'm going to die
Okay and this can be
great If you can teach
how to touch the diamond
world you can really see where you are going
next you will know details such details
that you will even know Who will be your
teacher in the next
life starting from a very early
age you will see your
teachers so you are
relaxed So the five forces on how
to live a good
life How to use these same five forces
when death comes to us
want to be so
serious just
enjoy your
life your teachers all your friends They act like they are
not
going to we are all going to die so let's
make it
beautiful actually it's quite
fun there is a misunderstanding in
our
heart when all our lives we
pretend that we will die that we will never
die we try to
ignore the biggest thing in our
life When you get and so ra
it will actually relax you very much Okay Well
now I know what to
do
Great learn
learn how we are going to die
before we die
then you already  We are ready and prepared, we
can learn this this
week, the Hara teachers can help you with
this for the next 3 months, support
you, they will teach you classes
in a couple of
days and you will receive 18 meditations over
several
days. Let's
learn how to
die, and then you put this instruction
in your breast pocket and
live your life according to the
basics, when you get hit by a
car, you are like Yeah, I have the
SBO instruction, and then we are
ready. I am not trying to be
depressed now, for me it is very
relaxing when I know what will
happen. I know where I will go, where I will go,
I know who will be at the
next bus
stop, and I will just
relax. Dava pobu, we are
always
late today.
So, we will take a short break.
Alex
Rice. Will sing for us, perform a
song for us. Don't be
nervous, everything is
fine. Alexi, pao, in my opinion. Where is pao
anyway?
Ana, in my opinion.
So, five
forces. I hope that the teachers will
give someone 100
dollars tomorrow, so now I
am returning
the money and you check. Five forces in order to
live. Five forces in order to
ut
So we call
white white white
Selya the second is
habit the
third is
Decision making is the
destroyer and the fifth is
prayer Brian List five white
seed
habit
decision
Destroyer and prayer and let's go
five the names are the same for
living and for
dying please don't be so
serious when we talk about
death if no one taught you how to
die then you should be really
serious then next if someone
teaches how to die then you should
rejoice
Great abbreviation
I once visited this place this cell
where he sat in prison and was sentenced to
death It's next to the Agora market in
Athens and the government ordered him to
beat out the
poison
because he taught strange things to
young
people called
philosophy and he's about to
get drunk now I'm like oh well oh well big deal
drink
stopped Tai bo look
Nago is
burning no no no
no I borrowed a chicken from a
neighbor so that it would lay me
eggs Please return the
chicken later  and drank the
poison he was not afraid of
eri
So white
seed so collect accumulate good
seeds your
problem as a person
lama you will not steal money from
people you will not kill anyone
Of course this is this you will not do don't
sit around who should I
go
kill today This is not our
problem our problem is what
Which is the best
seed Which of these two
good ones because I don't have time to
do all the good
deeds so I need to set
priorities which is the most powerful good one
I
[music]
can your problem
which is the best of these two good
seeds you don't have
time there was a
student he was from
berm his name was
Nal and I tell him I will teach you a new
meditation he says just just
slow down Everything you don't need
anything in the World Cup the problem is you have already taught me a lot of
meditation
now e one te so that I
don't perform meditation every morning
our problem what is the
problem white se
means
ro because we don't have time to
do all the good
deeds too many
good ones
but we need to know each of them
Why do I have money
[music]
no e repeat
question  We don't have time to do all the
good
deeds. Even though
everyone is good, they will train to be a
teacher, not
lice. Therefore, we need to
prioritize, we need to choose
la uchi more and more and more.
Now tell me, why for 100
dollars, so that we could pass it on to
others, we could pass it on to teach it to
others. Yes, 100
dollars was donated to me by someone, a
strange Mexican guy
with Thai
roots. We need to study good deeds
every
day,
because every person
here who is present here will someday
become a
teacher. When you come into this
room, a
contract, an agreement,
to teach someone
else what you will teach here, to
teach two people in the kitchen.
In the morning, why not
two of you, or you can sing a song in front of
a thousand-strong
audience and then teach them. After
that, you
hear for free, listen for free. The agreement is that
you signed that you
must share.
This is because there is such a Doctor.
The shortage is like the Kalahari. 5 million
people and 10 doctors among all these 5
million. Here is a team of five doctors,
serious doctors, that's why we have a shortage of
doctors. All these 5 million, they  someday they will
die and none of them know how to
die properly, so we have a
serious shortage of streams that teach
death. When you come to
classes, our
traditions,
you have already signed an agreement to teach
this to
others, of course, you don’t need to stand up in front of an
audience of 6,000 and sing them some
song, at least teach someone in a
coffee shop, maybe they don’t know that you are
teaching them, they won’t even understand it. It’s
clear that I learned how to die here this morning, after all, it’s
[music].
The more you study, the more you
learn, the better for you, because
each patient needs their own special
medicine. You should have a large
suitcase with different types of medicine so that
you can choose the
right one for that particular
person.
Of course, he takes all the pills
he
asks for. This is not very
good, practice what you need, but
you learn everything, and this is the first of the
five white power of the white
seed in order to live, how to live, how to
live properly. I hope
Grandpa will have time to tell you everything today. The
second one is a very famous teaching, boo boo.
In direct perception, they are
constantly in direct perception of emptiness it
doesn't matter if
they are standing, walking, or
sleeping, sitting, walking, or walking,
what do we do all day? We
do one of these: sitting, standing,
and in meditation, meditation of direct
perception of
emptiness, during meditation of direct
perception, to prepare for
this, you need to follow the second of the
five
forces, and this is called
habit. What does it
mean? When you sit down, think about
someone. When you sit down,
think about someone. When
you sit down, think about how I can
help someone. When you stand up and
stand, think about how you can
help someone. When you take the first
step, think about how you will help
someone. Think
about how you can even
help someone when you are in a
laugh. It doesn't matter which of the four. Which of the
activities you do, just
develop this
habit. There is a picture here, or
not.
Let's look at
this. This is called a constant,
endless flow, and habit
is called a
flow. Something continuous, no matter whether you sit, walk, stand,
or
sleep. You find all the time. When you have
one and the same  the same thought in the background How can I give
someone the next
picture this is called the habit of
eating vegetables I don't have such a
habit Green
here green green
this is a famous quote about
vegetables you and I have
someone
says I need a
lung transplant and we are like I
hope you find a
suitable one and honestly I don't have the
courage to give someone a lung I understand
maybe one day I can do
this but at the moment I am like this I need
both of mine So
we think but shantideva
say start at least with vegetables
Brian
When you give someone vegetables or a green
smoothie
then you say a little
prayer I hope one day I can give
someone my lungs with the same ease as I
gave my green drink they get
scared when they hear these stories about
ahwah he cut off his hand gave it to someone
gave it to
someone there is a funny
story in
India the right hand is for
eating and they don't use spoons welcome
they eat with your hands you take rice with your hands and
always eat it with your right
hand
because the problem with
toilets in every toilet there is a cush with
water before going to the toilet
check if there is
water there should be enough water
water a
bunch of toilet paper yes no toilet
paper is not always available
toilet clean yourself clean yourself it
is called the Diamond Way it
is called left-handed Ronnie on the left
side left side is important in the Diamond
Way to give up the left
hand and someone asks Bats to give up his hand
such a story and he says with his right hand
more
it is more
developed he cuts off his right
hand and offers his left hand to his right hand
AT
such a left
hand
more
This is a famous example in general
he says goss of
course he regretted
this I will now
we are with you on the
second
it is a
habit You need to get used to
everything If you make a habit out of it
You can get used to
everything first you give up your hand it is
difficult the second time it is
easier for us it is not
different
we talk about
it but we are not allowed to cause
our forbidden reasons our because this
body is
obviously and we need to try to laugh
egi lyu maybe a
million years but now take care
of your body and you don't need to do anything
some such practices that
will cause
good next
and he says
Listen when
you are at a young
age a glass of water and you don't know how to
listen to it you
don't know how to get close to pouring
this
water there are funny photos
like Maitri throwing an avocado on the wall the
first
avocado which He
tried naen when le
even lifting a
cup is difficult for us and we need to
learn this then we become
better and better at it And he says listen
giving up your
hand is difficult at first and then then Everything
happens automatically it's the same as
you pick up a cup of coffee you don't even
think about it you
just give it
This is because of the second
force of
habit So you have taken the cup 300,000
times already and it's already
automatic it's the same as you
learn to drive
Zara You can talk with m
and it will be almost automatic
At first it's difficult then you get
used to it in
our when we sit and you hear someone who is
sad for example at the
beginning we are so irritated
a little Lord an hour now he will
tell how bad he is how
heavy he is at the very
beginning and
when he finishes I want to
go I don't have time to hear l an hour
someone
died at least once  Do this then the
second time it will be easier the third time You are
already helping other people this is
also a habit,
just speak English
Start and It will become a habit of helping
others
People it becomes
easier
good to
eat
with it
seems I didn't want this picture let's
follow I still need to go back Tes to the
cup he
says while you are little you can't
even lift the
cup
you spill the
water you are used to and it becomes
automatic he says you understand your
understanding of
Rima will also become automatic will come to
you
automatically you will become like a lama in
Tibet
when They mount a
horse they put their
feet and
first leave the stirrup then they
throw their leg over with
ease then insert the second
Rem
and before putting the first one the
second they can read the entire
meditation this
time before you with
Bezos the moment when
then it is
clear we will just slowly start
[music]
the car Show us the next
sentence gompa It begins yes Please
highlight Yes in general all two
lines Highlight a
lot of things you
heard what your grandfather told you over the
past few years you can find
in this
dream from time to time We
return to  this sentence I think
you've heard it said many
times
here The Tibetan word for
meditation is to make it a habit The
Tibetan
word for meditation is
compa repeat
com and make something a
habit make habits
koms If you comm then this has
become a word meaning
meditation So the word meditation in
Tibetan means to make something a
habit make it a habit in
Sanskrit it's very
interesting
repeat
and the
verb to be comes from this word
means to do
that when we add
sui anli ut
teacher music musician Yes the one who
performs
actions create new create a new
person create a new person this is
beautiful this in
English the one who performs
actions means existence and
Sanskrit
the word for
[music]
meditation
in
Tibetan
means to form a
habit create a new
person and these words they denote
layer meditation I think this is very
beautiful the fourth
power us
VM
lists in order I don't know
why you can by the way ask
the students a question so they can discuss Why And in
that order
what will be a very nice
picture
in my  There are a
lot of stray dogs in the monastery
in Third World countries, this is quite
normal
for our monastery. This was a
problem with dogs. They start at someone's
home, then they get lost,
and then the dog begins to learn to live on the
street, and they become
dangerous, and they gather in
packs, and this is really very
dangerous. 20 dogs in a pack run down the street, and
you're
so scared.
So, there is a habit in Tibet.
When you see this pack of
dogs, you squat down very quickly
because you need to quickly understand the
stone in order to make it in time. The
dogs understand
when I tell you how to walk down the
street.
If you see more than TH
teenagers, too. Sit down,
especially if it's a
girl. In any case, this becomes
a habit. You do this. This is an
automatic picture of
flies. To drive away a fly, it
lands on your
nose, and there you go.
When you
meditate, you must
have incredible self-control
not to wave your hand. Sometimes I let them
crawl on my
face. I sit and they
crawl like that, but when they come in, of course, they
reach my stray, I begin.  The
end of
the meditation. If
you are in a place where there are a lot of
flies, buy this mosquito
net. You can put it on your
head when you
walk. Take your moto with you.
It's
good. We're talking about the World Cup here.
Thursday, we
had
destruction.
The Destroyer. What does this mean? What does this mean?
You squat down
and this
means. Every time you start
thinking about what
you're
doing. This is what it
should be like. Flies on your
jacket, but automatically. Take a
stone. What does this mean? This means
destruction. And you worry
only about what you want and forget about
what
others need. You must form a habit
so that once you start
thinking,
this must become an instinct. This must
happen
instinctively and
automatically. Alright, you are the army of all
people. Yes, this must become your
automatic habit when
I get mine. Think
about something
else. Stay for
coffee. Every time a thought appears. I'm talking about
simplicity and this is the force of
destruction. Three forces have finished about how to
live and I owe you two more forces about how to
live and five forces about how to
die, so we will have a short
break.